<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumphant and sumptuous arch erected by the Company of English Marchants residing in Lisbone, vpon the Spanish Kings entry made thereinto Togither with the architecture thereof described, the painted quadrants, the figures of halfe and whole stature, the ornaments, iewels, rich vestiments, the histories, ænigmes therein employed, with their declarations; and the Latine mottoes, and Spanish verses expressed in English. Wherein also, mention is made of the magnificent present the Duke of Braganza gaue to the King, the number of the traine that followed him, the wonderfull prouisions, and buildings set vp for the Grandes of Spaine, with the other lords and seruants of his Maiesties court, the salues of artillery, with the fires and lights that were made all ouer the citie, on the day that he came within sight thereof, to Almada, a place on the other side of the riuer, halfe a league distant, and right ouer against Lisbone. Faithfully translated out of the Spanish originall.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09563</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849857</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09563)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1213:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumphant and sumptuous arch erected by the Company of English Marchants residing in Lisbone, vpon the Spanish Kings entry made thereinto Togither with the architecture thereof described, the painted quadrants, the figures of halfe and whole stature, the ornaments, iewels, rich vestiments, the histories, ænigmes therein employed, with their declarations; and the Latine mottoes, and Spanish verses expressed in English. Wherein also, mention is made of the magnificent present the Duke of Braganza gaue to the King, the number of the traine that followed him, the wonderfull prouisions, and buildings set vp for the Grandes of Spaine, with the other lords and seruants of his Maiesties court, the salues of artillery, with the fires and lights that were made all ouer the citie, on the day that he came within sight thereof, to Almada, a place on the other side of the riuer, halfe a league distant, and right ouer against Lisbone. Faithfully translated out of the Spanish originall.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] G[riffin] for Henry Seile, at the Tygers head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Spanish original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-B4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philip --  III, --  King of Spain, 1578-1621.</term>
               <term>Lisbon (Portugal) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>British --  Portugal --  Lisbon --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arches, Triumphal --  Portugal --  Lisbon --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15029:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15029:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRIVMPHANT AND SVMPTVOVS ARCH erected by the Company of Engliſh Marchants reſiding in LISBONE, vpon the Spaniſh Kings entry made thereinto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Togither with</hi> The Architecture thereof deſcribed, the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Quadrants, the Figures of halfe and whole ſtature, <hi>the Ornaments, iewels, rich veſtiments, the Hiſtories, AEnig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes therein employed, with their declarations; and the Latine mottoes, and Spaniſh verſes expreſſed in Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein alſo, Mention is made of the magnificent preſent the Duke of BRAGANZA gaue to the King, the number of the traine that followed him, the wonderfull prouiſions, and buildings ſet vp for the Grandes of Spaine, with the other Lords and ſeruants of his Maieſties Court, the ſalues of Artillery, with the fires and lights that were made all ouer the Citie, on the day that he came within ſight thereof, to Almada, a place on the other ſide of the Riuer, halfe a league diſtant, and right ouer againſt LISBONE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Spaniſh originall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>E.G.</hi> for <hi>Henry Seile,</hi> at the Tygers head in Paules Churchyard. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15029:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15029:2"/>
            <head>THE KING OF Spaines entertainment into LISBONE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt other aſſignments and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions made by the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Citie of <hi>Lisbone,</hi> (at the requeſt, and for the peculiar of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of ſome Nations there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding) of certaine parts and quarters, by which his Maieſtie was to enter, and paſſe, there was allotted to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the firſt Port of the Citie walls, which is the Arche, called the olde <hi>Pelourino,</hi> for which the two litle Arches of ſtone, and the houſes ſtanding thereon, were demoliſhed, leauing ſome fiftie hands breadth of entry, and an hundred &amp; ten in height, the which, with the fifteene, that the Figure takes vp, that finiſheth the Arche, makes a hundred twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fiue, there remayning on the top of the Port, fortie foure in the concaue, twenty foure in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and on the ſides, fiftie in height and twenty ſeauen in breadth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:3"/>In the firſt Quadrant ouer the Architecture of the ſaid Port was cut in whole ſtature the ſtatue of the Citty of <hi>Lisbone,</hi> in a rich veſtement imbroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, with a Crowne on her head, holding in her right hand two keyes, one of ſteele, ſignifying her ſtrength, and the other of gold, implying her wealth and opulence; who extending her hand, offered them to the King. Her left hand ſhee repoſed vpon an Anchor of gold, to note, the ſuſtentation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhee enioyes by the Sea, with the Citie armes hanging thereon, which are a ſhip, in which the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyr <hi>S. Vincent,</hi> her Patron, came thither, to take harbour, and vnderneath it this inſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Liſbone</hi> the great, a Citie of renowne,</l>
               <l>The faire Metropolis of Portugall;</l>
               <l>Famous for loyall ſeruice to the Crowne,</l>
               <l>As likewiſe for her ſtrength and courage tall:</l>
               <l>To offer to your Maieſtie is bold</l>
               <l>Theſe keyes, this golden anchor, and this ſhield,</l>
               <l>With all the worth and power ſhe doth hold.</l>
               <l>In which, ſhee giues you, all hir bounds can yield.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the Quadrants, that comprehend this picture, in the midſt was delineated the taking of <hi>Lisbone</hi> by the King <hi>Don Alfonſo Henriques,</hi> together with the ayde of a ſtrange Nauie, which being in their courſe towards <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> miraculouſly there took Port. On the right hand is pourtrayed the King with the Prince his ſonne, and ſome other great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, &amp; by them his Armie: &amp; in the left Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, <hi>William Long-Eſpée</hi> Earle of Saliſbury, with
<pb facs="tcp:15029:3"/>
his Engliſh nobilitie, who accompanied him, to the winning of this Citie, and ouer his owne, the armes of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> being a Croſſe of gold enameld, with other foure Croſſes of the ſame: as likewiſe in the ſame Quadrant hard by him, is painted and ſet foorth his whole fleete, of an hundred and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore ſaile, with this inſcription vnderneath:
<q>
                  <l>The faithfull <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which with faire pretence</l>
                  <l>Doe ſoiourne now within this famous place;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe that many of their ancient race</l>
                  <l>Did hold therein their noble reſidence.</l>
                  <l>And got this paſſage like victorious Peares</l>
                  <l>Ioyning the ſtrength of <hi>Portugall</hi> to theirs.</l>
                  <l>Though Strangers counted; yet with humble hearts</l>
                  <l>Will be the firſt ſhall ſerue your hie deſerts.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the other Quadrant aboue this Figure, which formes the Arch, there are fiue perſonages raiſed in whole ſtature, each of them being twelue hands breadth in height. One was <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> ſonne to the King of <hi>England,</hi> arm'd onely with a gorget, his gauntlets, and coate of male, with his Spaniſh cape, a hat on his head, and a plume of feathers in it, after the Engliſh faſhion; at his feete his Scutchion of armes, which are the golden Lyons of <hi>England:</hi> and for a difference from the Scutchion of armes royall, a red-roſe: he was portraied, giuing with his right hand his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Catherine,</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and with the left his daughter <hi>Philip,</hi> to King <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Portugall</hi> the firſt, they being very gallantly clad
<pb facs="tcp:15029:4"/>
after the Engliſh manner, and the Kings Statue in the ſame forme as the Dukes, each of them in their vſuall attire, and habite, and at their feete, their Scutchions of armes: that of <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> being a Croſſe of Auis, of which Order hee was Maſter, and this inſcription vnderneath.</p>
            <q>
               <l>From theſe two Ladies of Great <hi>Brittaines</hi> Iſle,</l>
               <l>The faire remembrance of whoſe glorious worth,</l>
               <l>Doth now enrich the Kingdome of Caſtile,</l>
               <l>And ſets with honour <hi>Luſitania</hi> forth;</l>
               <l>Long ſince did your Progenitors deſcend,</l>
               <l>As by this ſtory you may plainely know:</l>
               <l>And for this cauſe, great Monarch we pretend</l>
               <l>That you your Hearts-loue to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> owe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Vpon the Baſe, which is the full Continent of this Architecture, ſtood <hi>Saint George</hi> on horſbacke treading vpon the Serpent, in manner and forme as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> weare him, for their Patrone, and beareth ſuch an inſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <l>He did, being Patron to great <hi>Englands</hi> King,</l>
               <l>Aſsiſt the <hi>Portugall</hi> in euery thing.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Alluding to the ſignall that the <hi>Portugalls</hi> made of his name, in companie of theſe Strangers which aided them, as we may ſee, in the battaile of <hi>Saint George.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the inward parts were two Impreſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on the vpper part, which expreſſed the intent of the Quadrants, in this forme. On the one part
<pb facs="tcp:15029:4"/>
are deciphered two Faulcons flying in the aire at an Herne, which at laſt yeelding, they ſeaze vpon, with this Motto: <hi>Eodem parta labore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other are two trees, which grow from rootes conioyned, ſpreading their tronckes broad and wide, being farre diſtant one from an other, out of their branches come two braces of armes, in forme as if they would claſpe and embrace, with this Motto annexed; <hi>Donec iungantur &amp; ipſae.</hi> On the vpper part of the Arch there is another Impreſe, of the Grandes, or Great-men, of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> which are painted on the ſides of the gate. There is portraied the Sun beating with his beames from on high vpon two chriſtall Looking-glaſſes, which with reciprocall beames, reuerberate and giue light one to another, with this Motto: <hi>Alter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri lucet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the right ſide, which anſwereth iuſtly to the Quadrant of <hi>King Don Alfonſo,</hi> there is placed in foure Niches, foure demy ſtatues, of braſſe coulor'd, which were foure famous men of <hi>Portugall,</hi> that exalted themſelues in <hi>England,</hi> in dignitie, and by armes. The firſt was, the Infant, <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> ſonne to King <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Portugall,</hi> who was Knight of the Order of the Garter in <hi>England</hi> (where he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed many Heroicall Actes) with an azure ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, and Engliſh letters, expreſſing thus much in French: <hi>Honi ſoit, qui mal y penſe.</hi> Which is the Motto, or Inſcription of the ſaid Order, and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a Scutchion of his royall Armes: and for his Impreſſe a Crowne of Oake with akornes, in the midſt of it, a Ballance, and at his feete, this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:5"/>
               <l>I am <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> th' <hi>Infant</hi> of great fame,</l>
               <l>Renowm'd for Armes in euery forraine State;</l>
               <l>None yet my valour euer ouer-came,</l>
               <l>But the harſh Enuie of my cruell Fate.</l>
               <l>Braue <hi>Englands</hi> King, ſaw my atcheiuments ſuch</l>
               <l>He did me Knight with warlike Hand:</l>
               <l>Nor thought the honour of his Garter much,</l>
               <l>For one ſo famous in a Stranger-land.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond was the Infant, <hi>Don Henrique</hi> his Brother, Knight of the ſame Order, and afterwards Maſter of the Order of the Knights of Chriſts in <hi>Portugall,</hi> with a blew Garter, and the ſaid letters written: a royall Scutchion or ſhield, and in the ſaid ſhield a barre of difference, and at each end thereof three Flowers <hi>De luce</hi> round about the ſhield, as it were abroad Belt, which reacheth to the Button, and in it the ſame Poeſie of the Garter written, bearing for a creaft, a Crowne of Oake, with the habite of his Order in the midſt of it, and at his feete this Inſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> am I, who in my boſome bring</l>
               <l>True wiſedome with me, courage, hie-command;</l>
               <l>Sonne to that warlike, and heroike King,</l>
               <l>Who honoured <hi>Portugall</hi> his natiue land.</l>
               <l>By my exploites within the <hi>Engliſh</hi> coaſt</l>
               <l>I there the Order of the Garter gain'd:</l>
               <l>From thence returnd with my victorious Hoſte,</l>
               <l>The Maſterſhip of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> I here obtaind.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:5"/>The third was <hi>Iohn Vaſquez, d' Almada,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Aluaro Vaſquez,</hi> Count of <hi>Abranches,</hi> who perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many noble exploites in <hi>England,</hi> where hee died: he weareth the honourable Order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereof he was Knight, and the armes of the <hi>Almada's,</hi> in his Scutchion, with theſe verſes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Much celebrated is my worth and fame,</l>
               <l>From the Sunne riſing to his going downe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohn Vaſquez</hi> of <hi>Almada</hi> is my name;</l>
               <l>Who gaue one Earle more to the French kings crown:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> hath knowne the mettaile of this ſword;</l>
               <l>For <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Caſtile</hi> it ſtoutly ſtood:</l>
               <l>Faire England me her Garter did afford,</l>
               <l>And ſweetly harbourd my congealed bloud.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The fourth was <hi>Ayres de Silua,</hi> who remaining in <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Portugall</hi> Embaſſador, for his worthy demerit, was made Knight of the Honourable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Garter, he weareth his Order bearing in his Sheild a Lyon rampant of the <hi>Siluas,</hi> and at the foote this inſcription:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ayres</hi> I am of <hi>Sylua</hi> by my name</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Luſitanian</hi> borne, &amp; one whoſe fame,</l>
                  <l>In euery corner of the world doth ring;</l>
                  <l>Sent with an Embaſie to <hi>Britaines</hi> King</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loue by courtly carriage I obtaind,</l>
                  <l>And by my wiſedome ſuch acceptance gaind;</l>
                  <l>That now each Prouince doth entitle me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saint Georges</hi> Knight a ſtile of hie degree.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:6"/>In the Quadrant right againſt that of <hi>William Long-Eſpée</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> there are foure other famous perſons of <hi>England</hi> which made themſelues renowmed in <hi>Portugall,</hi> by their valiant and heroike actions. The firſt was <hi>Edmund</hi> ſonne to the King of <hi>England,</hi> who valiantly aided King <hi>Don Ferdinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> of <hi>Portugall</hi> in his warres. He hath his Scutchion of the armes royall of <hi>England,</hi> with the difference of a red-roſe, and theſe verſes vnderneath.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Great <hi>Edmund</hi> I, the ſonne of <hi>England's</hi> King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe valiant arme great victories did bring</l>
               <l>To <hi>Portugall,</hi> and to his natiue land,</l>
               <l>Led by the guiding of great <hi>Ferdinand:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With warlike Heart I did my ſelfe addreſſe,</l>
               <l>To meete my foes, where dangers moſt did preſſe.</l>
               <l>Whereby much fame to <hi>Britaine</hi> I acquir'd</l>
               <l>And <hi>Spaine</hi> throughout my Proweſſes admir'd.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond was, <hi>Aymon</hi> Earle of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſon to the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> who atchieued maruellous enterpriſes, in this kingdome, in the vauntguard of the Royall battaile of <hi>Saint George;</hi> At his feete hee hath this inſcription:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Poet fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſome Spaniſh Author (as it ſhould ſeeme) hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken the right Engliſh names, which (gentle Reader) you must pardon.</note>Sprung from the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> am I</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haymon</hi> by name of courage bold, and ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Th' Earledome of <hi>Cambridge</hi> was my dignity;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Portugall</hi> did ſound my praiſes out.</l>
                  <l>With her I conquer'd oft, through freindly chance;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spaine</hi> knew my Virtues did ſo far extend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15029:6"/>That highly ſhe my glory did aduance;</l>
                  <l>And ioy'd that I did from her Kings deſcend.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The third was <hi>Don Liberche,</hi> who aſſiſted King <hi>Don Alfonſo,</hi> at the taking of <hi>Lisbone,</hi> and from him, and his Followers, the towne of <hi>Almada</hi> tooke her name, of which they were Lords: In his ſhield he beareth the armes of his name, and theſe verſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath ſubſcribed:
<q>
                  <l>Full oft made I the proud <hi>Barbarian</hi> feele</l>
                  <l>The keener edge of my well-temp'red ſteele.</l>
                  <l>And made this paſsage triumphe in their bloud,</l>
                  <l>That ſought to force it, gainſt the publike good.</l>
                  <l>Since when <hi>Almada</hi> hath her name retaind,</l>
                  <l>From him and his who thus her ſafety gaind.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Portugall</hi> doe know</l>
                  <l>What loſſe the Mores by him did vndergoe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth was <hi>Don Chil de Rolim</hi> (to whom King <hi>Don Alfonſo</hi> gaue the royaltie of <hi>Azambaia,</hi> and from whom, the <hi>Rolines,</hi> and <hi>Mores</hi> of this kingdome diſcend) with his Scutchion of Armes, and this poeticall ſubſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> by birth, in worth I did abound,</l>
               <l>And was the firſt, that ſought by force of Armes</l>
               <l>To lay theſe Rampiers leuell with the ground,</l>
               <l>Frighting the Mores with many fierce alarmes.</l>
               <l>By my renowmed and thrice glorious Fame,</l>
               <l>I ſatisfie the Houſe, which from me came,</l>
               <l>More then <hi>Zambaia,</hi> which to me befell,</l>
               <l>A pettie Lordſhip, and a little Cell.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:7"/>On the backe part of this worke, there are two Quadrants, which take vp the whole Baſe of the Figures, in the greateſt whereof, Corporall Force, or Valor is pourtrayed in the forme of a luſtie yong man armed, being of robuſtious members, and haughtie aſpect, his helmet reſting vpon a marble Columne, his armes powdred ouer with harts, trampling vnder foote, a Trophie, of banners and armes of all kindes; and ſomewhat lower hard by his ſide, two women, repreſenting the Engliſh and Portugall Nations, to whom, he ſtands preſenting a Palme, and crowne of Lawrell, and at his feete theſe verſes ſubſcrib'd,
<q>
                  <l>That looke ſo much deſired, which with ſmiles</l>
                  <l>The hearts of Men combines and reconciles,</l>
                  <l>Not ſuffering Valour to admit Diſtrust,</l>
                  <l>Nor Mildneſſe to be trampled in the Duſt;</l>
                  <l>Hath now by Force and his Aſsociates made,</l>
                  <l>Peace twixt two Nations, which ſhall neuer fade.</l>
                  <l>And Warre diuides the Lawrels, which ſhe brings,</l>
                  <l>Alike to Englands, and to Caſtiles Kings.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the litle Quadrant, which finiſheth the whole worke on the backe part, anſwering to the Quadrant of the Alliances, and Mariage, is painted a Lyon, and a Leopard, one bearing the Sheild of Spaine, the other that of England, with ſharpe pointed ſwords goaring and thruſting one at an other, yet in the midſt of the ſame ſwords towards the points, two Oliue branches were drawne, being the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles of peace, with this motto,
<q>Iam mutata, quieſcunt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:7"/>The conceipt of this Impreſe is, that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Nation did hereby intimate to the King, their noble demerit in the Conqueſt of <hi>Portingall,</hi> by their ancient deſcent, and the inviolable amitie they haue retained with the Kings of this Kingdome, implying further, their deſire of loue and peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Kings of Great Britaine and Spaine.</p>
            <p>The King entred into Portingall, on the eleuenth of May, <hi>ſtilo novo,</hi> with extraordinarie demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both of ioy and magnificence, (which ſhall be ſpecified in an other relation) in the number whereof, the greateſt and moſt worthy of note was, that the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> with his ſon the Duke of <hi>Bracelos,</hi> came to entertaine him with a 1000 men in their traine, betwixt ſeruants &amp; the aſſiſtance of his name &amp; familie. He preſented the King with three hundreth Bucks, an hundred Beafes, two thouſand Muttons, two thouſand Connies, foure thouſand Hens, two thouſand paire of Peacocks, foure thouſand Pigeons, foure thouſand Chickens, two thouſand gammons of Bacon, and a great quantitie of ſweet meats, with bread, wine, fruits of the ſeaſon, and many other things of great price, and eſteeme. He prepared alſo ſufficient prouiſions for all the Kings Courtiers, and ſeruants, ſo as till this day, there was neuer a more famous thing ſeene. The King made his entry into <hi>Elues,</hi> and from thence he went to <hi>Eſtremos,</hi> and ſo paſſed to <hi>Euora,</hi> where the Inquiſition preſented him, with their acts and ceremonies. On friday being the foure and twenty of May, he went to <hi>Caſillas,</hi> and <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15029:8"/>
halfe a league croſſe the riuer, right ouer againſt Liſbone, and that night both by land and Sea, there was a triumphant peale of great ordinance in the Citty, and there were ſo many fires made, and lights burning in euery houſe, that the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thereof, appeared like a burning Globe. A ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor was ſpread, that he would ſecretly view the Proceſſion, of the <hi>Corpus Domini,</hi> and that from thence, he would goe downe to the Monaſterie of <hi>Belin,</hi> where he would remaine till Thurſday the thirty of Iune, the Feſtiuall day of <hi>S. Antonie</hi> of <hi>Padoa,</hi> on which day it is conſtantly affirmed, that he will make his ſolemne entry into Liſbone. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aduertiſements ſhall be publiſht hereof in due time, and in the meane while, thoſe things which haue ſucceeded and paſt, ſhall be imprinted more at large, according to the forme and deſcriptions ſent in writing, from <hi>Don Gabriel Formento,</hi> Chaplaine to the Marques of <hi>Alenquer,</hi> Viceroy and Captaine Generall of the Kingdome of Portingall. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe other vnderſtanding Gentlemen, and worthy of credit, who haue bin herein ſued vnto, to afford their true relations, as eye-witneſſes of the Kings entries, into <hi>Merida, Medellin, Truxillo, Badaioz,</hi> and <hi>Elues,</hi> haue not as yet ſent theſe their reports, this preſent diſcourſe is prefixed, but as they are ſent or come to hand, they ſhall be divulged and made knowne incontinently.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15029:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
